Finding Aid for the Miriam Matthews papers LSC.1804
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Subject Files, 1845-1988
  - Negro in California--history, 1969-1972, undated. (Box 13, Folder 4)
    Research notes, correspondence.
  - Negro music and drama programs, 1944-1945. (Box 13, Folder 5)
    Paul Robeson, Hilda Simms, Dorothy Maynor, Anne Brown, and Muriel Smith are featured.
  - "New York's black elite"--article, undated. (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Our Authors Study Club--souvenir programs, 1954-1961. (Box 13, Folder 7)
    Los Angeles Branch of the Association for the Study of Negro Life and History
  - Our Authors Study Club--souvenir programs, 1965-1974. (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Pleasant, Mary Ellen, 1925-1933. (Box 14, Folder 1)
    Correspondence of C.W. Bell, Boyd Stutler, and Stella Ingram Brown, researchers of Mary Ellen Pleasant.
  - Pleasant, Mary Ellen, 1934-1938. (Box 14, Folder 2)
    Correspondence of Boyd Stutler, and Stella Ingram Brown, researchers of Mary Ellen Pleasant.
  - Ramsey, Eleanor, 1979-1980. (Box 14, Folder 3)
    Correspondence--California historic resources inventory.
  - Ray, Francis Marion, 1973. (Box 14, Folder 4)
    Photocopy of biography of grandfather by Clarissa Mae Hundley
  - Roberts, Frederick Madison, 1952, undated. (Box 14, Folder 5)
    California legislator, editor, and mortician. Photographs, copies of clippings.
  - "Roots" discussion, undated. (Box 14, Folder 6)
    Miriam Matthews' research and notes for discussion of the film "Roots" in Los Angeles
  - Schomburg Center for Research in Black Culture, 1976-1978. (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Selznick, David O., 1976. (Box 14, Folder 8)
    Program for "Producer prince: a celebration of David Oliver Selznick."
  - Shackleford, James, 1966, undated. (Box 14, Folder 9)
    Research notes and photostats of articles and photographs.
  - Shaw, Leslie, 1985 March. (Box 14, Folder 10)
    Clipping and funeral program.
  - Smith, William E., 1938-1951, undated. (Box 14, Folder 11)
    Photostats of clippings, research notes and biographical sketch.
  - Spectrum: 200 years in Los Angeles, 1980. (Box 14, Folder 12)
    Photocopy of grant proposal.
  - Spencer, Vaino, 1980 October 29. (Box 14, Folder 13)
    Photocopy of clipping.
  - Still, William Grant--clippings, 1941-1966. (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Still, William Grant--clippings, 1970-1975. (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Still, William Grant--correspondence and biographical notes, 1970-1978, undated. (Box 15, Folder 2)
    Correspondence between Miriam Matthews and the Still family; biographical notes.
  - Still, William Grant--programs, 1955-1979, undated. (Box 15, Folder 3)
    Programs of musical performances and tributes.
  - Still, William Grant--publications, 1939-1975. (Box 15, Folder 4)
    Includes "Troubled Island" libretto signed by Langston Hughes.
  - Takara, Kay Brundage, circa 1977. (Box 15, Folder 5)
    Photocopy of essay.
  - Temple, Ruth, 1939, 1969-1983. (Box 15, Folder 6)
    Physician and founder of Community Health Association. Photocopies of clippings, biographical notes.
  - Turner, Rufus P., after 1982. (Box 15, Folder 7)
    1907-1982, electrical engineer, technical writer. Biographical sketch and list of publications.
  - University of Chicago, 1953, 1965. (Box 15, Folder 8)
    Publications.
  - Uprising--newspaper, 1968 April, 1968 May. (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Watts, California, 1965, 1971. (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Weekes, Leroy, 1979 May 5. (Box 15, Folder 11)
    Tribute program.
  - William Grant Still Community Arts Center, 1978-1982. (Box 15, Folder 12)
    Administrative records, event programs, clipping.
  - Women For, 1970-1970. (Box 15, Folder 13)
    Women's volunteer support and action group. Newsletters, pamphlets.
  - YMCA, YWCA, 1941-1972. (Box 15, Folder 14)
    Pamphlets, newsletter.
  - Black California, 1940-1947, 1963-1982, undated. (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Blodgett, Louis, circa 1924, 1962-1965. (Box 16, Folder 2)
    Brother-in-law of Miriam Matthews. Clippings, handwritten notes by Miriam Matthews.
  - Boyd, Robert, Mrs., 1956, 1970, undated. (Box 16, Folder 3)
    Obituary, clippings, photocopies of photographs of Emma Boyd.
  - Bunche, Ralph J., 1950, 1971-1980. (Box 16, Folder 4)
    Copies of speeches made at United Nations Inauguration Ceremony for Ralph Bunche Memorial Sculpture, clippings, programs.
  - California history, 1947-1949. (Box 16, Folder 5)
    Bibliography
  - California report, 1978. (Box 16, Folder 6)
    "State Programs and Appointments with Impact on Black Community"
  - Churches--First A.M.E. Los Angeles, 1925-1972. (Box 16, Folder 7)
    Clippings, photocopies of book pages, programs.
  - Churches--Lincoln Avenue Methodist and Second Baptist, 1926, 1983. (Box 16, Folder 8)
    Program, clipping.
  - Clayton, Mayme, 1973, 1981. (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Cloud, Frank, 1936, 1970. (Box 16, Folder 10)
    Photocopies of Cloud's Children's Pictorial, biographical sketch, photographs by Frank Cloud, Naval Air Station program
  - Coffey, Alvin, 1902, 1937, 1950, undated. (Box 16, Folder 11)
    Clippings, correspondence, biographical sketch.
  - Community Health Association, 1950, 1970-1980. (Box 16, Folder 12)
    Minutes, correspondence, health pamphlets. Founded by Ruth Temple, M.D.
  - Community Reporter, 1959-1977. (Box 16, Folder 13)
    Newsletter of Community Relations Conference of Southern California.
  - Compton, California, 1970, 1980. (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Fair housing and employment, 1946, 1958-1978. (Box 16, Folder 15)
    Memos, pamphlets, newsletters.
  - Fowler, John, circa 1937. (Box 16, Folder 16)
    Photocopied book, "Spreading Joy," a collection of his columns in the California Eagle.
  - Gordon, Walter, 1938-1976. (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - Henry, Mary Bradshaw, 1979 March 1. (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - Johnson, Nelle, 1975 July 6. (Box 16, Folder 19)
    Clipping, "Requiem for Aunt Nelle." Ralph Bunche's aunt.
  - King, La Vetta, 1977 August 7. (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - League of Allied Arts, 1939-1976. (Box 17, Folder 2)
    Programs, clippings. Includes "The Negro Speaks of Rivers" signed by Langston Hughes.
  - Leidesdorff, William Alexander, 1849-1855. (Box 17, Folder 3)
    Microfilm printout of estate inventory and probate court record, pages 1-15.
  - Leidesdorff, William Alexander, 1849-1855. (Box 17, Folder 4)
    Microfilm printout of estate inventory and probate court record, pages 16-33.
  - Leidesdorff, William Alexander, 1845-1864, 1949, 1956, 1974. (Box 17, Folder 5)
    Copies of correspondence, articles, map of Spanish California.
  - Los Angeles Black pioneers, 1927, circa 1920s, undated. (Box 17, Folder 6)
    Clippings. Four publicity photographs of James Lowe from the film Uncle Tom's Cabin. There are ten photographs of unidentified women and men and the 34th Street Fire Company firefighters
  - Los Angeles Black settlers--article, 1975. (Box 17, Folder 7)
    Clippings of six part series, "Los Angeles Black Settlers and Lies of Negro Pioneers," published in Los Angeles Sentinel. Research notes of Miriam Matthews who cited many inaccuracies in the articles.
  - Los Angeles Civic League, after 1932. (Box 17, Folder 8)
    Pamphlet.
  - Los Angeles--Fire Department, 1898-1900,1966-1974, undated. (Box 17, Folder 9)
    Clippings and Miriam Matthews research notes.
  - Los Angeles--Founders, 1946-1966. (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Marsh family, 1954,1967, 1970. (Box 17, Folder 11)
    Photocopied clippings and programs relating to Vivian, Leon Sr., and Leon Jr. Marsh
  - Miller, Loren, 1962-1967. (Box 17, Folder 12)
    Clippings, biographical sketch.
  - Motion picture companies--Black, 1921, 1969, 1977. (Box 17, Folder 13)
    Copy of articles of incorporation of Lincoln Motion Picture Company and list of George P. Johnson Negro Film Collection, clippings.
  - Negro bibliographies, 1930-1942. (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - Negro in California, 1914-1927, 1952-1976. (Box 18, Folder 1)
    Clippings, photocopied programs.
  - Netherland, Mary C., 1916, 1970, 1971. (Box 18, Folder 2)
    Granddaughter of John W. Scott, a soldier with Colonel John C. Fremont. Clippings.
  - Olympic Games--Los Angeles, circa 1932. (Box 18, Folder 3)
    Ticket stubs, photocopies of promotional materials.
  - Our Authors Study Club, 1964-1979. (Box 18, Folder 4)
    Program, clippings.
  - Pleasant, Mary Ellen, 1969-1970. (Box 18, Folder 5)
    Correspondence and notes of Marjorie Green, biographer of Mary Ellen Pleasant.
  - Pleasant, Mary Ellen, 1862-1867, 1904, 1930-1947, undated. (Box 18, Folder 6)
    Photocopied correspondence, court records, clippings, relating to Mary Ellen Pleasant.
  - Pleasant, Mary Ellen, 1895-1899, 1933-1946, undated. (Box 18, Folder 7)
    Photocopied articles and Miriam Matthews research notes, clippings. Two photographs of unidentified women.
  - Politics--Los Angeles, 1959-1985. (Box 18, Folder 8)
    Clippings, newsletters.
  - Politics--Westside Republican Women's Club, Federated, 1958-1967. (Box 18, Folder 9)
    Photocopies of clippings, programs, commendations.
  - Programs--miscellaneous, 1917-1934, 1949, 1970. (Box 18, Folder 10)
    Photocopies of news clippings and programs of plays, church events, funerals in Los Angeles. From the collection of Mrs. Jessie Terry's brother.
  - Reference and bibliography--University of Southern California, 1944. (Box 19, Folder 1)
    Guide for School of Library Service.
  - Russell, Clayton, 1942, 1981, undated. (Box 19, Folder 2)
    Photocopies of World War II speech, funeral program, newspaper clipping.
  - San Diego Pioneers, 1937, 1958-1969, undated. (Box 19, Folder 3)
    Photocopied clippings, book pages, about Nathan Harrison, Allen Light, and the pioneer life.
  - San Francisco, 1974. (Box 19, Folder 4)
    "A Walking Tour of the Black Presence in San Francisco during the Nineteenth Century" by Elizabeth Parker and James Abajian.
  - Scott, David Gillis, 1926. (Box 19, Folder 5)
    Obituary.
  - Scott, Margaret, 1943, 1962-1969. (Box 19, Folder 6)
    Clippings, biography, Sojourner Truth Industrial Club program, obituaries. Two photographs of Miriam Matthews at Margaret Scott's 103rd birthday party.
  - Silhouette Pictorial--magazine, 1939 February, March, October, 1940 September. (Box 19, Folder 7)
    Photocopies of issues.
  - Spikes, Benjamin and John, 1942-1951. (Box 19, Folder 8)
    Benjamin "Reb" Spikes, composer, author, music publisher. John Spikes, composer, author, conductor, teacher. Photocopied programs and articles.
  - Still, William Grant-musical scores, undated. (Box 19, Folder 9)
    Photocopies.
  - Still, William Grant-"Lenox Avenue", after 1936. (Box 19, Folder 10)
    Signed by William Grant Still and Verna Arvey to Ivan and Dorothy [Johnson].
  - Still, William Grant-Phylon article, 1951. (Box 19, Folder 11)
    Notes and correspondence of Miriam Matthews.
  - Still, William Grant, 1938-1978. (Box 19, Folder 12)
    Clippings, correspondence from Judy Still Headlee, program.
  - Tackett, Marnesba, 1981 July 22. (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Towns, Royal E. & family, 1970, 1977. (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - Trends in race relations on the West Coast--a symposium, 1949. (Box 19, Folder 15)
    Photocopies of articles from Common Ground, volume IX, number 3.
  - Wilfandel Club officers, 1949. (Box 19, Folder 16)
    Photograph from brochure.
  - William Grant Still Community Arts Center, 1977-1978. (Box 19, Folder 17)
    Clippings, dedication program.
  - Williams, Paul R., 1930-1977, undated. (Box 19, Folder 18)
    Clippings, biographies, lists of buildings Williams designed.
  - Williams, Paul R., 1976, 1978. (Box 19, Folder 19)
    Historic-Cultural Monument designation of residence, Musilog project.
  - Alexander, Titus, 1896-1936. (Box 20, Folder 1)
    Correspondence, clippings, medical school entry tickets.
  - Alexander, Titus, circa 1914-1924. (Box 20, Folder 2)
    Scrapbook
  - Blodgett, Louis and Ella, 1940-1962. (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Bunche, Ralph J., 1963-1983. (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Community Health Week, undated. (Box 20, Folder 5)
    Poster.
  - Fowler, John, 1937. (Box 20, Folder 6)
    "Spreading Joy," a compilation of columns from the California Eagle.
  - Johnson, Ivan J., III, circa 1934. (Box 20, Folder 7)
    Scrapbook.
  - Miriam Matthews Exhibition Placards, undated (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Johnson, Ivan J., III, 1940. (Box 21, Folder 1)
    Scrapbook of clippings and photographs relating to California assemblyman campaign.
  - League of Allied Arts, 1974, undated. (Box 21, Folder 2)
    Clippings, program honoring the 5th Dimension.
  - Leidesdorff, William, 1847-1848. (Box 21, Folder 3)
    Microprint and copy of San Francisco Town Journal during tenure as treasurer.
  - Los Angeles Black pioneers, circa 1910s-1920s. (Box 21, Folder 4)
    Clippings, photographs of unidentified women
  - Moore, Clement C., undated. (Box 21, Folder 5)
    Clipping about "The Night Before Christmas."
  - Negro History Bulletin, 1938 May - 1940 May. (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Pleasant, Mary Ellen, 1899 July 9. (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Still, William Grant, 1964 February. (Box 21, Folder 8)
    Ebony article.
  - Westbrook, Yvonne, 1971 October 24. (Box 21, Folder 9)
    Clipping about election bid for San Francisco Board of Supervisors.
  - Williams, Paul R., 1940- circa 1963. (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Alexander, Titus, undated (Box 22, Folder 1-9)
  - Alexander, Titus, undated (Box 23, Folder 1-7)
  - Stevens, Virginia, undated (Box 24, Folder 1-7)
- Personal Papers, 1927-1977
  Personal correspondence and memorabilia
  - Correspondence and personal papers, 1927-1977. (Box 5, Folder 8)
    Correspondence. Photocopy of 1927 study list with grades, University of California Alumnae News Notes, and photograph of Matthews at Los Angeles Public Library. Photograph in newspaper clipping. Letterhead. Address book, notes.
- Museum and Exhibition Posters, 1984, 1985, undated. (Box 25)